so let's talk about the role of the
storage in a computer system it keeps
all the files the programs the data all
the settings the operating system
everything and also
our virtual memory is implemented using
storage
because we cannot fit all the data that
the application actually wants to access
to physical memory
some of those pages are actually on disk
and when the program accesses them they
are loaded into the physical memory
but meanwhile they're sitting
in our storage for example on our disk
so storage is important not only to keep
data but also to extend
our virtual memory so that we think we
have more memory than we actually have
for both uses of storage we care about
performance
mainly
throughput and latency throughput is how
many bytes per second can we get out of
our for example disk
latency once we request
a page of data when are we going to get
it back
and in storage this
is improving but not as quickly as the
processor speed is improving whereas the
latency
is improving
but very slowly
the reduction in storage latency is even
slower than the reduction in dram
latency
so processors are getting faster and
faster dram is getting faster but
lagging behind processors and becoming
slower and slower relative to the
processors and that storage is falling
further behind dram itself in addition
to performance we are also really
concerned
with reliability if our processor fails
our system temporarily doesn't work
until we replace the processor but then
we can boot up the system and it works
again but if our disk fails
we lose our programs data settings etc
which is much much worse
than just a processor failing so we are
much more worried about the reliability
of our storage than we are about most of
the other elements of our computer
system
and finally the types of storage that we
can use are very diverse we can have
magnetic disks our traditional hard
drives optical disks such as cds and
dvds
tape
for backup
flash drives that are much faster than
most of the other ones and so on